Guide to the Mattie Underwood Russell Papers, 1949 - 1988 UA.29.02.0059
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mattie Underwood Russell papers
1949 - 1988
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Russell, Mattie U.
UA.29.02.0059
5 Linear Feet
Mattie Underwood Russell (1915-1988) was Curator of the Duke University Manuscripts Department from 1952 to 1985. During these years, Russell became a nationally-recognized archivist, and increased the number of collections, implemented a cataloging system, and encouraged researchers to use the materials in the Manuscripts Department. The Mattie Underwood Russell Papers include correspondence, reports, writings, subject files, memoranda, and other materials related to Russell's career at Duke University. Major subjects include archival administration, archival education, American history, southern history, the Duke University administration, and the Nixon presidential library controversy at Duke University. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Records of the University’s Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Provenance
The Mattie Underwood Russell Papers were received by the University Archives as gifts in 1985, 1988, and 1989.
Biographical Note
Mattie Underwood Russell was born on May 14, 1915, in Pontotoc County, Mississippi. She grew up on her parents' farm, the youngest of 12 children. She attended the University of Mississippi, earning a bachelor's degree in 1939 and a master's degree in 1940, both in history. Russell worked from 1937 to 1943 teaching high school in rural Mississippi, earning her academic degrees during the summer. In 1943, she moved to Durham to attend a summer session for teachers at Duke University, then moved to Mars Hill, North Carolina to teach as a faculty member at Mars Hill College. In 1946 she returned to Durham as a fulltime Ph.D. student and worked in the library at the circulation desk.
While she completed her Ph.D., Russell became Assistant Curator of the Manuscript Department in 1948, and in 1952 she became Curator. In 1956, she completed her Ph.D. degree in history, with a disseration on William Holland Thomas, a white chief of the Cherokee tribe, but it was archives and manuscripts to which she devoted her life's work. As Curator, a position she held until 1985, she improved the scope of the collections exponentially. During her tenure the Manuscript Department grew from approximately 1 million items to over 7 million items. Russell encouraged her staff to provide better access to the collections for researchers through the implementation of a cataloging system. She also mentored new members of the profession through her work at Duke and her teaching. From 1969 to 1978, Russell taught a course on archives and manuscripts at the School of Library Science at the University of North Carolina.
Russell was a member of many professional organizations, including the American Library Association, the Society of American Archivists, the Historical Society of North Carolina, the Southern Historical Association, and the South Atlantic Archives and Records Conference. She served as a representative of the Southern Historical Association on the National Archives Advisory Council from 1977 to 1983. She was named a fellow in the Society of American Archivists in 1979. In 1981, Russell was the only non-faculty member appointed to the Academic Council's committee to study the possibility of locating Richard Nixon's presidential library on the Duke campus. In addition to her professional and university committments, Russell also published many articles in history and library journals.
Upon her retirement in 1985, her colleagues donated money to create the Mattie Underwood Russell Endowment Fund, used to purchase manuscript collections pertaining to the history and culture of the Americas, particularly the United States. Following her death on May 4, 1988, a bequest from Russell's estate to the Endowment was one of the largest contributions Duke has ever received from an employee.
Collection Overview
The Mattie Underwood Russell Papers include correspondence, reports, writings, subject files, memoranda, and other materials related to Russell's career at Duke University. The collection is divided into five series. The first series, Correspondence, includes both personal and professional materials. In arranging the correspondence, Russell included genealogy, printed material, and other material she felt were pertinent to the correspondence. The series is arranged chronologically. The second series, Subjects, is arranged alphabetically, and includes information about Russell's professional interests as well as biographical and other personal information. Course Materials, the next series, includes information collected during Russell's teaching career in the School of Library Science at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. The materials are arranged alphabetically by subject. The fourth series, Writings, includes addresses, articles, and other pieces written by Russell. The series is divided into "Addresses and Lectures" and "Writings," and materials are arranged alphabetically into these categories. The last series is the Nixon Presidential Library series, which includes a proposal, correspondence, reports, and committee materials.
Related Material
Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL) Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Nixon Library Controversy Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
University Archives Photograph Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Southern States -- History; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting; Presidential libraries -- United States; Archives -- Administration; Archivists -- Training of -- United States; United States -- History; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Library. Manuscript Dept; Duke University -- Employees; Russell, Mattie U.; Duke University. Library
- Correspondence, 1949-1988
  Scope and Contents note
  On the first folder of this series, Mattie Russell noted, "In 1969 I decided to go through the small amount of personal correspondence I had saved and decide what I should like to have become part of a collection in the Manuscript Department of Perkins Library under the title, Mattie Underwood Russell Papers. To this correspondence, I added genealogy, miscellany, clippings, and printed material. My plan is to add to this file consistently during the remainder of my life."
  - 1949-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - January 1970-June 1970 (Box 1)
  - July 1970-December 1970 (Box 1)
  - January 1971-June 1971 (Box 1)
  - July 1971-December 1971 (Box 1)
  - January 1972-June 1972 (Box 1)
  - July 1972-December 1972 (Box 1)
  - January 1973-June 1973 (Box 1)
  - July 1973-December 1973 (Box 1)
  - January 1974-June 1974 (Box 1)
  - July 1974-December 1974 (Box 1)
  - January 1975-June 1975 (Box 1)
  - July 1975-December 1975 (Box 1)
  - January 1976-June 1976 (Box 1)
  - July 1976-December 1976 (Box 1)
  - January 1977-June 1977 (Box 1)
  - July 1977-December 1977 (Box 1)
  - January 1978-June 1978 (Box 1)
  - July 1978-December 1978 (Box 1)
  - January 1979-December 1979 (Box 1)
  - April 1979-August 1979 (Received after my surgery on April 10, 1979) (Box 1)
  - January 1980-December 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981 (Box 2)
  - January 1982-December 1982 (Box 2)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988 (Box 2)
- Subjects, circa 1968-1987
  - Art (Box 2)
  - Automobile, Volare Premier, 1978 model, purchased January 2, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Book Reviewing (Box 2)
  - Capital Campaign, Faculty/Staff Committee, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Certificates (Box 2)
  - Canada papers, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Land Use Policy, March 1987 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Retiree Association (Box 2)
  - Endowment, Mattie Underwood Russell Endowment Fund, 1985, May 14- (Box 2)
  - Endowments, Duke University Library (Box 2)
  - Robert H. Woody Festschrift
    - Bibliography of Robert H. Woody and Biographical Data (Box 2)
    - Biographical Sketch of Robert Hilliard Woody for the Festschrift compiled in his honor and published in the South Atlantic Quarterly, Winter 1974 issue (Box 2)
    - Dissertations written under the direction of Dr. Robert H. Woody (Box 2)
    - Replies to letter of June 25, 1970, in honor of Dr. Robert Hilliard Woody (Box 2)
  - Friends of the Library, Duke University, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Fringe Benefits, Faculty and Staff (Box 2)
  - Historical Society of N.C. Constitution, etc. (the other records I accumulated as president I sent to Carolyn Wallace on 4-27-77 to be used by her and then placed in the archives of the Society) (Box 2)
  - LC (Box 2)
  - Manuscript Department Communications (Box 2)
  - Memberships and Subscriptions (Box 2)
  - Membership cards and certificates (Box 2)
  - National Archives Advisory Council, 1977, May 12-14 Meeting--Membership Lists and Code of NARS (Box 2)
  - Recommendations (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Recommendations are restricted.
  - Recommendations, Manuscript Dept (Box 2)
  - Retirement (Box 2)
  - Russell, Mattie Underwood
    - Bibliography and Biographical Data (Box 2)
    - Biographical Material (Box 2)
    - Certificates (see also MC 8) (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Diplomas (MC 8) (Box 2)
    - Genealogy (Box 2)
    - Library Endowment Fund (Box 2)
    - Memorial Services (including audio cassette tape) (Box 2)
    - Memory Book (Box 2)
    - Miscellany (Box 2)
    - Printed Material (Box 2)
    - Retirement Records, 1985 (retired 5-31-85) (Box 2)
  - Salary Notices (Box 2)
  - Southern Historical Association Program Committee for 1973 (Box 2)
  - Tobacco History Corporation, Inc. (Box 2)
  - UNC Report of Dean of School of L.S., 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Woody, Robert Hilliard - History of his Family (Box 2)
- Course Materials
  - The American Archivist (Box 3)
  - American Association for State and Local History (Box 3)
  - American Records Management Association (Box 3)
  - American Revolution Bicentennial (Box 3)
  - Andrews, Evelyn G. (Box 3)
  - Architecture (Box 3)
  - Archives and Private Papers: Outlines of the Archival Management Lectures given by Schellenberg in Atlanta, April 8-10, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Archives
    - Ancient (Box 3)
    - Arts and Architecture (Box 3)
    - Careers in (Box 3)
    - Church (Box 3)
    - Church - Sandra McAninch, Preliminary Study for the Development of a Guide to Manuscript Collections Related to Southern Religion as Held by Southeastern Repositories (Box 3)
    - College and University (Box 3)
    - Confederate States of America (Box 3)
    - Federal (Box 3)
    - Film (Box 3)
    - Foundation (Box 3)
    - General (Box 3)
    - Germany (Box 3)
    - Indian (Box 3)
    - International (Box 3)
    - Islamic (Box 3)
    - Jewish (Box 3)
    - Latin America and the Caribbean (Box 3)
    - Labor (also Historical MSS.) (Box 3)
    - Local (County and Municipal) (Box 3)
    - Music (Box 3)
    - Performing Arts (Box 3)
    - Political Parties (Box 3)
    - Popular Culture ("Pop Cult") (Box 3)
    - Professions (Box 3)
    - Publishing Houses (Box 3)
    - Regional (Box 3)
    - Science and Technology (Box 3)
    - Indian (Box 3)
    - State
      - Alabama (Box 3)
      - Florida (Box 3)
      - Georgia (Box 3)
      - Maine (Box 3)
      - North Carolina, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Ohio (Box 3)
      - South Carolina (Box 3)
      - Virginia (Box 3)
    - Women (Box 3)
  - Archivist's Code (Box 3)
  - Audio-Visual Materials (Box 3)
  - Autographs (Box 3)
  - Automation (Box 3)
  - Bibliography for LS 344 (Box 3)
  - Bibliographies - Mine (Box 3)
  - Biographies (Box 3)
  - Blacks, materials about (Box 3)
  - Book reviewing (Box 3)
  - British Manuscripts (Box 3)
  - British Records Association (Box 3)
  - Cataloging Manuscripts (Box 3)
  - Classified Documents (Box 3)
  - Collecting Manuscripts (Box 3)
  - Course Term Project, 1970- (Box 3)
  - Data Processing and Retrieval (Box 3)
  - Diplomatic (Box 3)
  - Editing, Historical (Box 3)
  - Grade Books (Box 3)
    Grade Books are restricted.
- Writings
  - Addresses and Lectures
    - Addresses (Box 3)
    - Preservation of Our Library Heritage, address delivered by M.U.R. at the Annual dinner of the Friends of the Library at Campbell College, April 7, 1978 (Box 3)
    - The Relationship Between the Records Administrator and the Historian (Box 3)
    - Starting a Local Archives or Historical Society, address given on November 20, 1975, at the Archives and Records Workshop of the Society of Georgia Archivists (Box 3)
    - What Has Happened to History in the Archival Profession? (Box 3)
    - Lecture, Georgia Archives Institute, August 10, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Writings
    - Benjamin Edward Powell (Box 3)
    - The Influence of Historians on the Archival Profession of the United States (Box 3)
    - Land Speculation in Tippah County, 1836-1861 (M.A. Thesis) (Box 3)
    - Sketches for the Dictionary of North Carolina Biography (13) (Box 3)
    - Student Writings (Box 3)
    - Woody, Robert Hilliard (Box 3)
    - Writings (Miscellaneous) (Box 3)
    - Writings (Published Copies) (Box 3)
- Nixon Presidential Library, 1981-1982
  - Confidential Presidential Library Proposal and Notes, 1981 (Box 4)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Includes Board of Trusteees materials. Restricted until 2031.
  - Correspondence and Documents, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Dr. Mattie Russell Files, 1981, undated (Box 4)
  - Reports, Correspondence and Other Information, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Sub-Committee of the Selct Committee on the Nixon Presidential Library, 1981, undated (Box 4)
  - Sub-Committee on Library Relations, Correspondence and Reports, September 1981-October 1981 (Box 4)